Guide to the Dodd, Mead & Company Records 1720-1986 MS 171
New-York Historical Society
Dodd, Mead & Company records
1720-1986
New-York Historical Society
Dodd, Mead & Company
MS 171
47 Linear feet in 53 boxes of various sizes.
The records of book publishers Dodd, Mead & Company consist of the administrative, financial, publicity, and publication records of the organization, with some family photographs and biographical material. The collection is especially rich in author contract summaries, profit/loss calculations for individual titles, printing histories and inventories of titles, and book catalogues. Although books in the collection extend back to 1720 and through the 1800s, the bulk of the collection are business records and these date primarily from the 1890s and into the 1970s, with a few earlier and later.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into 6 series:
Series I. Administrative Records, 1877-1972
Series II. Financial Records, 1870s-1981
Series III. Publications Publicity, 1889-1986
Series IV. Publication Records, 1890s-1980s
Series V. Biographical and Company History Documents, 1834-1975
Series VI. Books and Other Publications, 1720-1938
Biographical / Historical
This collection includes some of the records of Dodd, Mead & Company. The company was founded in 1839 by Moses Woodruff Dodd and John S. Taylor as a publisher of mostly religiously focused texts, commentaries, and sermons. Over time the partners of the Dodd family shifted and the company was reorganized twice before becoming Dodd, Mead & Company in 1876 under Frank Howard Dodd, Edward S. Mead (Dodd's cousin), and Bleeker Van Wagenen. The breadth of their publications also expanded to include contemporary fiction, how to books, encyclopedias (The International Encyclopedia Company was a subsidiary), poetry, historical nonfiction, and many international titles among others. In the 1920s-30s Dodd, Mead expanded, buying several smaller publishing companies. The company was bought as a subsidiary by Thomas Nelson Inc. in 1981, bought again by Gamut Publishing Company in 1986, and finally ceased operations in 1990.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored off-site and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The source of the material is uncertain, but appears to have been a gift of Justin G. Schiller, Ltd., circa 1990s.
Scope and Contents
The Dodd, Mead & Company collection consists of administrative records, financial records, publicity materials, and publication records. The administrative records include operating files such as board minutes, insurance policies, and salaries. The financial records include mostly stock books, financial reports, and analyses of profits, losses, and operating costs. Publicity materials include catalogues, brochures, and photographs of authors. Publication records consist mostly of copyright cards and other internal documentation related to the company's published works. These records expose the points of expansion within the company and reveal the reorganization and restructuring the company underwent as they evolved and technology progressed. The documents also include many family photographs and miscellaneous clippings and other documents that provide insight into the style and accomplishments of Dodd, Mead's leadership over time. There are also many books from the 19th century (and a few from the 18th century), mostly religious books Dodd, Mead published.
Related Materials
Dodd, Mead's archives seem to have been somewhat widely dispersed. Some repositories (there may be others) that hold the company's records are:
Indiana University, Lilly Library (Dodd, Mead mss., 1855-1992, LMC 2415)
American Antiquarian Society: https://www.americanantiquarian.org/Findingaids/dodd_mead_company.pdf
University of Delaware Library: Dodd, Mead & Company Archive, 1896-1974, #250) (a small collection with a focus on African-American authors).
Authors -- Photographs.; Publishers and publishing.; Books.; Booksellers' catalogs.; Financial records.; Minutes (administrative records); Obituaries; Photographs.; Stock certificates.; Dodd, Mead & Company -- Archives.; Zylstra, Freida, -1997
- Series I. Administrative Records, 1877-1972; 1.39 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes general administration records, including board minutes for Dodd, Mead and a subsidiary, International Encyclopedia Company. Other records relate to employees (e.g., attendance, compensation, lists), insurance, lease/rentals, and other matters. There is a small amount of correspondence, especially related to furnishings of a store at 35th Street and 5th Avenue (1899-1900) and letters of 1890 with directives from Edward Mead to employee Miles Nourse.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by format/subject.
  - Dodd, Mead Board Minutes (3 volumes), 1916-1950 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-3)
  - Transcript of Board Authorization for the President to have Purchase and Sale Power (concerning company holdings and stocks), 1941 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 7)
  - International Encyclopedia Company Minutes (3 volumes), 1909-1972 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 4-6)
  - Attendance Records, 1943-1944, 1951-1959 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 8)
  - Salaries, 1925-1961 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 9-13)
    Analysis and records by year consecutively, with some gaps. There are also bonus records from 1935-54 and an undated employee list.
  - List of Officers and Employees, 1924, 1928 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 3)
    Two lists, both cumulative showing all employees beginning in 1876.
  - Unexecuted Compensation Agreement between Stockholders and Management, 1941 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 37)
  - Insurance Policies and Related Material, 1956-1963 (Offsite-box 17)
    Includes: Insurance Audit; Insurance Policy, 1963; Insurance Policy, 1960; Fire Insurance Correspondence; Insurance Policy, 1956; Insurance Policy, 1961; Insurance Policy, 1963; Insurance Policy, 1963.
  - Lease Agreements, Correspondence, and Related Materials, 1937-1965 (Offsite-box 17)
    Includes: Lease agreements, 1937, 1941, 1945 (office), 1946, 1947, 1949, 1951, 1953, 1956, 1958, 1959, 1960, 1961, 1962, 1963, 1964, and 1965; Lease correspondence, 1953, 1954, and 1963; Window Cleaning Tenant Policy; Electrical Payment Record, 1964.
    Many of the letters in this file are written by Fred Slota, the former treasurer of Dodd, Mead, concerning a dispute about their lease. Slota engages in a heated exchange with their landlord before convincing him to lower the lease price. Many of the leases and other records contain related correspondence.
  - Correspondence re: Store and Office Construction & Furnishings, 1886-1900 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 4)
    Most of the documents date from 1899-1900 and relate to furnishing Dodd, Mead's store at 35th Street & 5th Avenue. A few earlier documents relate primarily to rentals.
  - Correspondence, 1879, 1891-1892, 1935 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 27)
    Primarily includes letters written to Miles Nourse by Edward Mead while at Southampton or in Europe conveying various instructions. Also an 1879 arrangement for sales commissions with J.F. Smith and a 1935 letter to E.H. dodd from George Wharton Edwards recalling the meaning of the colophon.
  - General Releases and Related Materials, 1877-1885 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 28)
    Defendants Leonard and Whipple among others.
  - Correspondence of J. Carrell Leiper and Loan Agreement, 1896 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence with the American Telephone and Telegraph Company, 1939 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 33)
    Includes photographs of the two telephone styles in use during the year of 1897.
- Series II. Financial Records, 1870s-1981; 13.75 Linear feet
  This series contains financial records of Dodd, Mead & Company and, to a limited extent, some of their subsidiaries. The series holds some financial reports for the company. The larger portion of the series consists of inventories, profit/loss analyses by book title, royalty calculations, records of company stock and bond holders, and other financial data.
  Arranged into two subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Financial Reports and Related Material, 1870s-1981
  Subseries II.B. Stocks and Bonds, 1909-1976
  - Subseries II.A. Financial Reports and Related Material, 1870s-1981; 9 Linear feet
    This subseries contains financial reports, particularly for the 1930s-1940s, inventories of stock of books and printing materials, and financial data, especially concerning book sales and royalties. The subseries features calculations of profit and loss by individual title, beginning with 1876 and ranging without gaps into the late 1950s; these annual analyses were referred to as "red books" because of the color of the binding used until 1944 (later years are on loose sheets, but retained the appellation). Also featured are inventories ranging from the 1940s to the 1970s. A number of miscellaneous financial matters close the subseries, among them royalty statements, securities transactions (investments) in the 1930s, copies of Dodd, Mead's billings for royalties, fees, and other payments due them, and other items.
    Arranged by format/subject, then chronologically.
    - General Analysis, 1903-1908 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 2)
    - Monthly Financial Reports (7 folders), 1935-1949 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 4-10)
      There are gaps in the date range.
    - "Red Books" (Profits and Losses by Title) (10 volumes), 1876-1944 (Offsite-box 34)
      The box holds nine books with a complete run from 1876-1944 of profit/loss analysis by book title. A tenth volume is labeled "copyright" but has financial calculations of some type for titles as well, 1879-1886.
    - "Red Books" (Profits and Losses by Title), 1945-1947 (Offsite-box 20)
    - "Red Books" (Profits and Losses by Title), 1948-1951 (Offsite-box 21)
    - "Red Books" (Profits and Losses by Title), 1949-1953, 1956, 1959 (Offsite-box 22)
      Includes general titles for 1952-1953 and 1956, with an overall analysis at 1959; and Juveniles for 1949-1953.
    - Inventories, 1940-1942, 1945-1949 (Offsite-box 19)
    - Inventories, 1950-1955, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 23)
    - Inventories by Author Name (box 1 of 3). E - K, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 24)
      This set of inventories, spanning three boxes, has entries primarily from the 1970s, with many from the 1960s, and a very few from the 1950s.
    - Inventories by Author Name (box 2 of 3). K - P, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 25)
    - Inventories by Author Name (box 3 of 3). P - W, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 53)
    - Inventories(?), 1978, 1981 (Offsite-box 23)
    - Book Sales & Royalty Calculations, 1930-1950s (Offsite-box 52)
    - Royalty Records. Sears Publications, 1930s (Offsite-box 17)
      Sears and its titles were acquired by Dodd, Mead.
    - Royalty Statements. Duffield & Company, 1931-34 (Offsite-box 7)
    - Book Rental Analysis, 1941-1945 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 16)
      Note on enclosure reads: "Showing dates of copyright, title, author, and kind of income used for excess profit taxes. Abnormal income."
    - Copies of Billings/Invoices by Dodd, Mead for Royalties Due, Fees for Reproductions, etc. (1 of 2), 1934-1945 (Offsite-box 27)
    - Copies of Billings/Invoices by Dodd, Mead for Royalties Due, Fees for Reproductions, etc. (2 of 2), 1945-1949 (Offsite-box 52)
    - Cash Collections. International Encyclopedia Company, 1917-1923 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 3)
    - Securities Transactions (4 folders), 1931-1933, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 11-14)
      Investment-related confirmations and correspondence with Fifth Avenue Bank Trust Department and broker Plympton, Gardiner & Co., 1931-1933. Also approved purchase list and other information about the Chemical Fund, Inc., with purchase confirmation, 1939-40.
    - Fiscal Year Record of Comparative Gifts, Dues, & Subscriptions, etc., 1941-1959 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 15)
    - Assorted Financial Records, 1873-1876 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
      The folder holds a summary of stock accounts, balances, and stock inventories, among other notes.
    - King Feature Syndicate Sales, Rights, and Related Correspondence, 1958-1965 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 22)
  - Subseries II.B Stocks and Bonds, 1909-1976; 4.75 Linear feet
    This subseries includes common and preferred stock and bond certificate books and books of account (i.e., record of investor transactions in the firm's securities). The certificate books include unissued certificates, cancelled/returned certificates, and stubs for issued certificates with details of issuance. The books also have related correspondence and other documents inserted.
    Arranged by company with Dodd, Mead documents first, followed by its subsidiaries. Within these, arrangement is by document type and chronological.
    - Book of Account, 1919-1960s (Offsite-box 26)
      Record of stockholder transactions.
    - Book of Account. Bondholders, 1916-1919 (Offsite-box 26)
      Record of bondholders (few entries).
    - Debenture Bonds Book, 1916-1919 (Offsite-box 14)
    - Common Stock Book, 1916, 1919, 1924 (Offsite-box 16)
    - Common Stock Book, 1926-1943 (Offsite-box 16)
    - Common Stock Book, 1945-1958 (Offsite-box 14)
      Wihin the stock book are also envelopes of documents concerning at least four estates: Edward H. Dodd, Jennie S. Dodd, Arthur M. Chase, and Howard C. Lewis.
    - Common Stock Book, 1958 (Offsite-box 15)
      This book holds mostly unissued certificates.
    - Common Stock Book, 1965-1968 (Offsite-box 15)
      This book also holds an envelope containing documents concerning the estate of Frank C. Dodd.
    - Common Stock Book, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 14)
    - Common Stock Book, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 14)
    - Preferred Stock Book, 1919-1939 (Offsite-box 16)
      Specific years included are: 1919, 1924, 1933, 1937, 1939.
    - Preferred Stock Book, 1945-1960 (Offsite-box 15)
    - Preferred Stock Book, 1966-1976 (Offsite-box 16)
    - International Encyclopedia Company. Book of Account, 1909 (Offsite-box 26)
    - Phelps Parker Company. Book of Account, 1916-1917 (Offsite-box 26)
    - Phelps Parker Company Stock Book, 1916-1920 (Offsite-box 26)
- Series III: Publications Publicity, 1889-1987; 7.85 Linear feet
  The series includes various publicity materials, including catalogues, brochures, logs and notices of upcoming publication dates, colophons, and photographs of authors. An unusual item for this collection are many original photographs taken by Freida Zylstra for the 1941 book "Skylark: A Story of a Girl Photographer Who Flew Over South America," written with the woman aviator Margaret Thomsen Raymond.
  Subseries III.A. Author Photographs and Related Materials, 1910s?-1960s
  Subseries III.B. Publicity Material, 1889-1987
  - Subseries III.A. Author Photographs and Related Materials, 1910s?-1960s (bulk, undated); 1.79 Linear feet
    While the purpose of some of these photographs remains unknown, many, especially those found in box 28, were photographs sent by author's agents to be hung in the office of Dodd, Mead & Company. Some may have also been used for promotional materials.
    Exceptional in this subseries and notable in substance are two folders with many photographs related to the publication "Skylark: A Story of a Girl Who Flew Over South America." One folder includes original snapshots that were printed in the book, and the other includes photos that were "left over."
    Photographs of the Dodds and related families are in Series V.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Anatole France, undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - Agatha Christie, 1950s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 9)
    - Arna Bontemps and Langston Hughes, taken by Griff Davis of Ebony, 1930s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 14)
    - Brick Church at City Hall Park (photograph of lithograph), undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 6)
    - Cornelia Otis Skinner, 1950s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence Concerning Framed Author Photographs on Office Walls, 1971 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 11)
    - "Crunch the Squirrel" by Elizabeth Anne Bond and Joan Elaine Rabin with illustrations by Kurt Wiese (mock-up), 1939 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 11)
    - Dodd, Mead Building, undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 10)
    - Elizabeth Seifert, 1940s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - James G. Randall, 1930s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 4)
    - Jean Henri Fabre, 1910s? (Offsite-box 51, Folder 13)
    - Loula Grace Erdman, 1950s? (Offsite-box 51, Folder 31)
      Includes negative.
    - Madame and Monsieur Maeterlinck, circa 1911? (Offsite-box 51, Folder 29)
    - Maureen Daly, 1940s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - Max Brand, 1930s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - Michael Innes, 1950s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - Office (509 Broadway), undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 31)
    - Office and Office Building Photographs (509 Broadway, etc.), undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 21)
    - "Sinbad of the Coast Guard" (photo with book, dog, and staff), 1945 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 31)
    - Photographs for "Skylark: A Story of a Girl Photographer Who Flew Over South America" by Margaret Thomsen Raymond and Freida Zylstra (1 of 2), circa 1940 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 19)
    - "Leftover" Photographs from "Skylark" (2 of 2), circa 1940 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 20)
    - Staff Photo, undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 31)
    - Three photographs of unidentified former employee given by his son, Clinton L, Mosher to Dodd, Mead officers, 1964 (Offsite-box 28, Offsite-box 15)
    - Unidentified Male Headshot taken by Hal Phyfe, undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Man, undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 7)
      Includes Negative
    - Unidentified Man, undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified Man, undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 8)
    - Various Author Photographs, 1952, undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 12)
      Photographs include: Loula Grace Erdman; Rutherford H. Platt; N. J. Bernice; Paul Laurence Dunbar; Edward Dolan Jr. (taken by Luther Green); Kenneth Grahame; Anatole France; Linus Pauling; Harold W. Felton; Phie Stong; Martha Ostenso; C. K. Chesterson; unnamed male, black and white head shot; Norman Douglas; Burton Stevenson; Guy GilPatric; H.V. Morton; Sydney Clark; George Sullivan; Frances Gray Patton; [?] Mantle; Agatha Christie; Cornelia Otis Skinner; James G. Randall; Admiral Edward Elsberg spring 1952; [?] Heacock.
    - W. Edmonds, undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - William P. McGivern, 1950s? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 17)
  - Subseries III.B. Publicity Material, 1889-1987; 6.06 Linear feet
    This subseries contains the publicity and promotional materials found in the Dodd, Mead records. This includes mostly catalogues and pamphlets as well as colophons and other printing materials. Among the catalogues, there are several standalone pamphlets that advertise a specific genre or collection (such as college textbooks). There are also several yearly catalogues that were all originally organized together and remain as such. These yearly catalogues include both Dodd, Mead and other publishing companies that were either subsidiaries or acquisitions of Dodd, Mead. There are also sets of bound catalogues that span several years and are inclusive of all the smaller catalogues that Dodd, Mead produced during that time period.
    Arranged by format then chronologically.
    - "A Selected List of New Books for the Holidays" Seasonal Catalogue and Promotional Material, 1917 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 39)
    - Publicity Brochures, 1974 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 2)
      Includes the following: Cover design and table of contents for "Black Politics" by Ernest Patterson and for "The American Democratic System" by J. Keith Melville; Dodd Mead College Books in Sociology Catalogue; Dodd Mead College Books in Romance Languages Catalogue; "German Zerts from Dodd, Mead" Catalogue; and Zig-Zag Puzzle Company Promotional Pamphlet.
    - Colophons (Dodd, Mead), 19th/20th Century (Offsite-box 51, Folder 18)
    - Company History Booklets, circa 1920s-1930s (Offsite-box 51, Folder 26)
      Includes two company history booklets, one printed by Dodd, Mead and the other by the International Encyclopedia Company. Also a remembrance written by Allison Dodd in 1939.
    - "First One Hundred Years" by Edward H. Dodd Jr. Manuscript and Notes, Circa 1939 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 38)
      Includes a photograph of Mrs. Dodd.
    - "The First Hundred Years: A History of the House of Dodd, Mead" by Edward H. Dodd Jr. Unbound, 1939 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence in Response to "The First Hundred Years" (2 folders), 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 23-24)
      One folder labeled "Dull" and the other "Interesting."
    - "Dodd Mead Some Suggestions For Authors" by Dodd, Mead & Company, circa 1937 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 6)
    - Dodd, Mead Christmas Cards (3), Circa 1900s (Offsite-box 51, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Ephemera, undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 16)
    - Log of books by publication date (?), 1899-1920 (Offsite-box 7)
    - Publication Slips, 1904-1939 (Offsite-box 7)
      Notices of which books are to be published on upcoming dates, with price.
    - Publicity and Building Photos (Offsite-box 51, Folder 9)
      Folder containing photographs and assorted materials of the Dodd, Mead building and publication and promotional materials. These various materials were found and remain together.
    - "The Retail Bookseller" Magazine, 1940 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 31)
    - Windmill Hill Stationery Cuts, undated (Offsite-box 51, Folder 42)
    - Individual Catalogues, 1914-1987 (Offsite-box 13)
      Catalogues from Dodd, Mead: 1961-1982, 1985-1987.
      Catalogues from other companies (acquired by Dodd, Mead): John Lane Company (1914, 1920, 1921); Duffield and Green (1933, 1934); Small, Maynard and Company (1926); Sears Publications (1933); Moffat, Yard & Co. (1923/24); Robert M. McBride & Company (1947, 1948).
    - Bound Catalogues. Vols 1-3, 1889-1903 (Offsite-box 17)
      Vols 1-3 (1892-1903), plus an earlier unnumbered volume for 1889-1890
    - Bound Catalogues. Vols 4-8, 1904-1914 (Offsite-box 33)
    - Bound Catalogues. Vols 9-14, 1915-1929 (Offsite-box 32)
    - Bound Catalogues. Vols 15-21, 1930-1948 (Offsite-box 31)
    - Bound Catalogues. Vols 22-26, 29, 30, 32, 1951-1982 (Offsite-box 30)
      Vols 22-26 (1951-65); no Vol 27, 28; Vol 29 (1972-74) for adult; Vol 30 (1975-78) for juvenile; no Vol 31; Vol 32 (1979-82) for juvenile.
    - List of Titles (untitled typescript), undated (Offsite-box 7)
- Series IV. Publication Records, 1890s-1980s; 20.25 Linear feet
  The series includes records generally of a non-financial nature related to Dodd, Mead's publications. These include summaries of contract terms with authors by title, records of copyright filings and renewals with the Library of Congress, and records of print/reprint runs and publication specifications.
  This series is arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries IV.A. Author Contract Summaries, 1890s-1970s
  Subseries IV.B. Copyright Records, 1890s-1960s
  Subseries IV.C. Printing Inventories, 1920s-1980s
  - Subseries IV.A. Author Contract Summaries, 1890s-1970s; 6.5 Linear feet